<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at VVhite-Hall, the third of December. By Robert Skinner chaplaine in ordinary to His Maiestie. Published by His Maiesties command</title>
            <author>Skinner, Robert, 1591-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12309</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121771</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856937</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856937</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22580</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12309)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22580)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1219:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at VVhite-Hall, the third of December. By Robert Skinner chaplaine in ordinary to His Maiestie. Published by His Maiesties command</title>
                  <author>Skinner, Robert, 1591-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by I[ohn] L[egat] for Andrew Hebb,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: [A]²  B-F⁴ G² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22580:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22580:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE THE <hi>KING</hi> at White-Hall, the third of <hi>December.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Skinner</hi> Chaplaine in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary to His MAIESTIE.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by His MAIESTIES command.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>I. L.</hi> for <hi>Andrew Hebb.</hi> 1634.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:22580:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22580:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 96. VERS. 9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>O worſhip the Lord, in the beautie of Holineſſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>NTERPRETERS vary about the occaſion of this Psalme: Some re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring vs to the placing of the <hi>Arke</hi> of God, in the citie of <hi>David;</hi> when with great solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it was brought from the houſe of <hi>Obed-Edom:</hi> Some reſolving it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to be ſung at the finiſhing of the <hi>Temple:</hi> but others, when the <hi>Temple</hi> was re-edified after the Captivity. And the truth is, all three opinions may well conſiſt, and be true all. For that it was ſung at the placing of the <hi>Arke,</hi> we have it expreſſely 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 16. And (all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducements
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22580:3"/>according) why might it not ſerve and be ſung, as well in the <hi>Temple,</hi> as before the <hi>Arke?</hi> and in the ſecond <hi>Temple,</hi> as well as in the firſt? which occaſioned the <hi>Seventie</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it as they did, A Song <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, after the Captivity, upon the reſtauration of the houſe of God. It matters not whether expoſition wee take; all give equall light to my Text; ſhew us what to vnderſtand by <hi>the beauty of Holineſſe,</hi> even the ſolemne place of his holy ſervice whom we are to worſhip; <hi>O worſhip the Lord in the beauty of Holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words at firſt hearing, foure particulars are obſervable. I. An hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, devout, religious act: <hi>Adorate,</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: II. the proper and peculiar ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Act: <hi>Dominum,</hi> the <hi>Lord.</hi> III. The ſpeciall place of this worſhip, recommended unto us by two proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: for firſt it is an <hi>holy</hi> place, <hi>in atrio Sancto,</hi> a place of Holineſſe; Then it is a <hi>beautifull</hi> place, <hi>in decore Sanctitatis, in the beauty of Holineſſe.</hi> IIII. We meete
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22580:3"/>with a ſtrong perſwaſion; an earneſt entreaty, Thus in this place to worſhip the Lord: <hi>O worſhip the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We ſee therefore what we muſt doe; we muſt <hi>worſhip:</hi> And whom we muſt worſhip; <hi>the Lord;</hi> And where the Lord will bee worſhipped, <hi>in his holy place:</hi> that if either beauty here, or ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctity, or dutie, or the Lord by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence can winne vpon vs, wee will bee worſhippers all; the powerful1 exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a King, the awfull incitement of a Prophet (both in the Text) ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline our hearts, and bend our knees, and direct our ſteps, <hi>O worſhip the Lord, in the beautie of Holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>What,</hi> firſt; <hi>Adorate Dominum: where,</hi> afterward: worſhip the Lord wee muſt; So we are commanded; but we cannot worſhip him aright, before we rightly conceive what it is to worſhip: Now take it at large, and to worſhip truly, is to give honor to another, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his worth; <hi>ſecundum excellenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> according to ſome excellent worth: For vvorſhip is not due to any, but to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:22580:4"/>that which is vvell worthy and that is of eminent vvorth: To worſhip one that is no way eminent, nor in any ſort a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove us, is an act of unworthineſſe, nor doe we ſo much honour him, as diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our ſelves: yee may call it baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or flatterie, or puſillanimitie; to all which, true worſhip is a ſtranger. <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> in the judgement of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> belong to ſome certaine per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; <hi>Honour to whom Honour belongeth, Rom.</hi> 13. And who are they? eminent at leaſt: nay, but the higheſt Honour is not due, ſave <hi>poteſtatibus ſupereminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus,</hi> to thoſe of the higheſt ranke, that are ſupereminent.</p>
            <p>True, wee are taught by the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>In giving honour, to goe one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore another:</hi> but wee ſhall finde it to hold upon this ground, <hi>That in lowli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of minde each eſteeme other better than themſelves, Phil.</hi> 2. Hee muſt bee our better, ſo wee muſt eſteeme him, (for ſome grace or other) wee cannot ſo properly honour him elſe; and if not <hi>honour</hi> him, much leſſe <hi>adore</hi> him: for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:22580:4"/>
               <hi>adorare</hi> is a great deale more than <hi>hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare:</hi> Yee may honour him for his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular gifts whom yee never ſaw, by a gracious tongue, or ſome honourable favour; but to adore, is ſo farre to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as to bow downe before him: As when <hi>David ſtooped with his face to the earth, and bowed himſelfe before King Saul,</hi> 1. Sam. 24. <hi>And Nathan the Prophet bowed himſelfe before King David, with his face to the ground,</hi> 1. King. 1. To adore then, is to honour in the higheſt degree, that is, with the lowlieſt expreſsion; briefely, to acknowledge anothers <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation,</hi> by our owne <hi>humiliation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, that I be not long in laying a foundation, there is ever implyed in <hi>Adoration</hi> a three-fold act: firſt, an apprehenſion of ſome excellencie or other; for if no kinde of preeminence be apprehended, wee doe not <hi>adorare,</hi> but <hi>adulari,</hi> worſhip wee know not what; whereas all true worſhippers are readie to ſay as our Saviour to the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of Samaria, <hi>We know what we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> Ioh. 4.22. Nor is it ſufficient to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22580:5"/>apprehend what is excellent, but wee muſt acknowledge alſo what wee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend; and our acknowledgement muſt be ſerious, and unfained: there will be otherwiſe, in ſtead of <hi>Adoration,</hi> plaine <hi>deriſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, moreover it is not complete wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, without a cleare Demonſtration of our ſubiection: without genufle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or proſtration, or ſome other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination or ſubmiſsion of the body. The very word here doth import as much: for the word in Hebrew (ſo often rendered by <hi>adorare</hi>) properly ſignifies <hi>incurvari,</hi> to aſſure us, our ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is lame and imperfect, unworthy the name, without an outward mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation: And we may note it in the Wiſe-men, that tooke ſo long a journey to worſhip, and knew the right forme wee may bee ſure <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>They fell downe and worſhipped, Matth.</hi> 2.11. And let me tell you, this was the manner of old when they came into the Sanctuarie; <hi>Venite adoremus, O come let us worſhip and fall downe;</hi> yes, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22580:5"/>when they went out from the Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie too; good <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and all his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, <hi>when they had made an end of offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, bowed themſelves and worſhipped,</hi> 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29. <hi>ver.</hi> 29. And now percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what it is to worſhip, let us further conſider whom we are to worſhip; <hi>O worſhip the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dominum,</hi> the Lord, even the Lord that made us, and not we our ſelves, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Lord Paramount, Lord of Lords, and God of Gods, even <hi>Iehovah,</hi> the Lord <hi>Almightie;</hi> And none I hope is ſo graceleſſe, as to ſticke at his worſhip: All will adore their Maker and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, the Author and preſerver of all things. Certainely, none are exempted or quit of his worſhip: Not the Angels in heaven; of them it is written; <hi>And let all the Angels of God worſhip him,</hi> Hebr. 1. Not any that are called Gods on earth; they are all commanded to doe their homage, <hi>Worſhip him all yee Gods,</hi> Pſal. 97. Not any Saints above: <hi>They all caſt downe their crownes and fall downe and worſhip him that liveth for ever
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:22580:6"/>and ever,</hi> Rev. 4.10. Nor any Saints be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: They daily cry out with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; <hi>Exalt the Lord our God and fall downe before his footeſtoole for the Lord our God is holy,</hi> Pſal. 99. There can be no queſtion, all are to worſhip, <hi>à vermiculo ad Angelum,</hi> from the baſeſt worme to the moſt glorious Angell; from him that ſitteth on the throne, to her that grindeth at the Mill, all come under <hi>Adorate Dominum;</hi> And know they muſt, in <hi>adoring</hi> the Lord, they <hi>honour</hi> themſelves; approaching thereby, and drawing neere unto the Lord; for if to be neere about a gracious King, bee iuſtly counted a ſingular grace, what an honor muſt it needs be, <hi>to be joyned to the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. to adhere and cleave to the <hi>King of Kings;</hi> to goe boldly <hi>to the throne of grace,</hi> and all this is daily done by adoring: Wee ſee then the dutie is generall, All are to worſhip, the Lord all, and that becauſe he is Lord of all.</p>
            <p>A chiefe point will be, for the manner, how: for we may not imagine, when the Prophet enjoynes us to worſhip the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22580:6"/>Lord, that his meaning is, wee ſhould worſhip him <hi>ad libitum,</hi> every one his owne way, according to his owne fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: Indeed wee would have it ſo; are ſtrangely taken with our <hi>owne inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> and were wee at a Looſe, what a various prodigious worſhip would be found amongſt us? For the <hi>manner,</hi> one ſitting, another ſtanding, a third kneeling, a fourth walking, a fifth lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: For the <hi>matter</hi> (when their tongues were their owne once) one ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious, a ſecond ridiculous, a third blaſphemous; and yet (if yee beleeve them) all true worſhippers, for all that.</p>
            <p>No, but <hi>Dominus</hi> the Lord, the very Name puts us in minde how he will be worſhipped; with what preparation, and with what devotion: Doe but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what a Lord, and then reſolve what kinde of vvorſhip vvill ſute him beſt. If ſuch a Lord as none like him, fit his vvorſhip ſhould be ſuch, as none the like. As no Lord equall to him, ſo no vvorſhip equall to his: No, but as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22580:7"/>we are praiſe him, ſo vve are to vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him; both <hi>according to his excellent greatneſſe,</hi> Pſal. 150.</p>
            <p>All Lords have one ſort of vvorſhip, or other; Soveraigne Lords <hi>ad terram uſque,</hi> downe to the ground. Thus to the King, <hi>and thus to the man whom the King will honour,</hi> Heſt. 6. But when all is done, all is but <hi>bodily</hi> worſhip, and that too <hi>Civilly</hi> intended, in Civill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpects: becauſe indeed, their higheſt Iuriſdiction, <hi>jus vitae &amp; necis,</hi> extends no further, is confined to the body: <hi>They have power only</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>to kill the body, and after that, have no more, that they can doe,</hi> Luk. 12.4. But the Lord here, hath abſolute power over ſoule and body and all we have, and ſo we to worſhip him with all: our ſoule he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired, our body hee ordained, our worldly goods vvhat vve have, he gave unto us; and our worſhip ſhould bee anſwerable: ſhall I ſhew you how?</p>
            <p>As briefely then as may be;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God is a ſpirit</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Iohn</hi>) <hi>and they that worſhip him muſt worſhip in ſpirit
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22580:7"/>and in truth:</hi> Ioh. 4. and looke vve vvell unto it, there is no deceiving him; for <hi>He ſearcheth the heart, and tryeth the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> Ier. 17. He is ſtyled by <hi>Moſes, the god of all ſpirits,</hi> and all ſpirituall wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip is due unto him: So peculiar is it to the <hi>Creatour</hi> as uncommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to any <hi>creature.</hi> Nor Saints, nor Angels, nor Principalities, nor Powers have any Dominion over the ſoule, to ſave or to deſtroy it, and therefore the bowings, and bendings of the ſoule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long not to them; Nay but all religious Divine, devout Adoration of the ſpirit or in the ſpirit, is entirely to be offered <hi>to the Father of ſpirits.</hi> If imparted to any other, <hi>ſive humilitate nimiâ,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De C. D. lib. 10. cap. 4.</note> 
               <hi>ſive a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulatione peſtiferâ</hi> (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaks) whether by too much humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or too much flattery, cleere it is, they that doe it, rob God of his honour; vvhich he tels us he vvill not endure: <hi>I am the Lord, that is my name, and my glory will I not give to another, neither my praiſe to graven Images,</hi> Eſai. 42.8.</p>
            <p>And when vve vvorſhip God vvith
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22580:8"/>our bodies, is it not alſo in a ſingular vvay? elſe it is not as it ſhould be; for <hi>Nathan</hi> to bow himſelfe before the <hi>Lord,</hi> and to bow before the <hi>King</hi> was it all one thinke vve? True, his body vvas the ſame, and his bowing much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, but infinite ods in his Adoration: Before the King as the <hi>Lords anointed,</hi> as the <hi>ſupreme miniſter</hi> of God for the Common good, In our Churches phraſe—<hi>In thee, and for thee, according to thy bleſſed word and ordinance.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord; as the work of his hands (and that by a word of his mouth) in a plenary ſubjection as well for being, as well being: Before the King, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in certaine circumſcriptions, of time, and place, and occaſion; But before the Lord, <hi>unreſtrainedly,</hi> in all places, at all times, upon all occaſions: whereby we confeſſe his illimited power his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall eſſence, his ubiquitary preſence; when we worſhip the Lord without bodies, it ought to bee with a ſpeciall Adoration: <hi>Quoniam ſi honos idem tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buitur allis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. a. Inſtit.</note> 
               <hi>ipſe omnino non colitur,</hi> A
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22580:8"/>good rule it is in <hi>Lactatius,</hi> If the ſame worſhip be given to any other, God is not worſhipped at all; What King will admit of a ſharer or co-partner, in his tribute or Homage? and what ſaith the Prophet? <hi>I am a great King, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Mal. 1.14. It were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge them to offer him a ſharer.</p>
            <p>Now for our Temporall eſtate, <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Dominum</hi> extends and comes up to that alſo: <hi>Honour the Lord with thy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi> ſo vve are commanded, <hi>Pro.</hi> 3.9. and good reaſon for it; for <hi>the bleſsing of the Lord it maketh rich,</hi> Pro. 10. And vvithout this bleſsing, in vaine vvere it <hi>to riſe up early, and ſit up late, and eate the bread of carefulneſſe.</hi> And though the World be unapt to beleeve it (incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous ever in vvhat is chargeable) the Lord expecteth vve honour him as vvell vvith our perſonall eſtates, as vvith our perſons: And how may that bee? By giving to the Lord <hi>in a proper way;</hi> by devoting ſome part of your plentie and ſuperfluitie to thoſe ſacred uſes vvhich redound immediately to Gods glory.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:22580:9"/>
            <p>The truth is, the Prophet chiefely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends it here; the vvords immediately afore my Text are, <hi>Bring, an offering, and come into his Courts:</hi> an Oblation vvas ever of old accounted a part of Adora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but I forbeare: <hi>Bring</hi> and <hi>offer</hi> are no pleaſing vvords, I know, though it be to the Lord; Take away, and hold faſt, vvithout any thought of reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this is the manner of too many, that yet vvould bee thought to deale very <hi>worſhipfully</hi> too; to vvorſhip God as vvell as the beſt, vvhen they ſpoyle him of that ſhould maintaine his vvorſhip. And <hi>will a man rob God?</hi> Mal. 3. Yes, and make the World beleeve they doe it for his honour: but their doome fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, vvithout repentance; <hi>Curſed with a curſe,</hi> verſ. 9. But I leave them to the mercie, of God: And it is high time I left this Point. I have done with the Act and the Object, <hi>Worſhip the Lord;</hi> onely remember, I beſeech you, How vve muſt <hi>worſhip,</hi> and how the <hi>Lord;</hi> it followes <hi>Where</hi> the Lord vvill be vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped: <hi>O worſhip the Lord in the beautie
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22580:9"/>of holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his holy Courts, in his holy San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie, in his glorious magnificent Sanctuarie; Thus, Interpreters varie: But <hi>Vatablus</hi> joynes with the Chaldee, and our Tranſlation followes both, <hi>In decore ſanctitatis,</hi> in the beautie of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: And the Scripture calls the <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie</hi> it ſelfe, the <hi>beautie of holineſſe,</hi> becauſe it was full of beautie and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. So (if yee marke it) the Points are three: The Lord will be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in a certaine place, proper for his worſhip; And the moſt proper place, is a ſacred place, or a place of Holineſſe; And a place of Beautie, as well as Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>O worſhip the Lord in the beautie of holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And it is well we are directed to a certaine Place: for ſhould the Place be uncertaine, our Service would be as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain as the Place. Time and Place have beene ever of ſingular moment in Gods Service: Were no <hi>Time</hi> preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, It were much to be doubted <hi>When:</hi> and were no <hi>Place</hi> appointed, it were
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:22580:10"/>hard to ſay, <hi>where</hi> we would worſhip: Wee may juſtly feare it, were no <hi>place</hi> aſsigned, <hi>adorate Dominum</hi> would bee ſoone out of Date; For <hi>who</hi> would thinke to worſhip, when hee ſaw not <hi>where?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may note it <hi>ſucceſsively</hi> in all ages never any tooke upon them to worſhip the Lord, but the <hi>place</hi> was reſolved on. Can we imagine, but <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> had where to bring their ſacrifices? And they that <hi>called on the name of the Lord,</hi> Gen. 4. had a place for their <hi>meetings,</hi> a <hi>meete</hi> place. After the flood <hi>Noah</hi> had his <hi>Altar</hi> where to adore, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. And ſo had <hi>Abraham</hi> his; even <hi>where the Lord appeared unto him,</hi> Gen. 12. expreſly cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>the place of the Altar,</hi> Gen. 13. <hi>Iſaac</hi> alſo erected an <hi>Altar,</hi> and <hi>there</hi> he called on the name of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. And when we reade that <hi>Rebeckah</hi> went <hi>to enquire of the Lord; quò perrexit?</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther went ſhee may wee thinke? even to the place of his holy worſhip; where the Lord would anſwer her, <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. And had not father <hi>Iacob</hi> his <hi>Bethel,</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:22580:10"/>by himſelfe, <hi>the houſe of God, and the gate of heaven,</hi> Gen. 28.</p>
            <p>When afterward the Children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael were upon often remooves in the <hi>wilderneſſe,</hi> the Lord ordained them a mooveable <hi>Tabernacle;</hi> to which every one <hi>reſorted that ſought the Lord,</hi> Exod. 33.7. and it was therefore called, <hi>The Tabernacle of the Congregation.</hi> But when the Church began to be happy in a ſetled ſtate, in the dayes of King <hi>David,</hi> his religious heart could no longer endure <hi>the Arke ſhould abide with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Curtaines, when he dwelt himſelfe in a houſe of Cedar,</hi> 2 Sam.7. And thereupon he <hi>vowed a vowe unto the mightie God of Iacob,</hi> Pſal. 132. <hi>But Salomon built him an houſe,</hi> Act. 7.47. And now the Lords people come hither all, whether to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive inſtruction, or expreſſe devotion; Here they addreſſe their vowes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence their prayers, preſent their obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions before the Lord; And this was the <hi>manner,</hi> till Chriſt came in. the fleſh.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:22580:11"/>
            <p>And what? when our <hi>Lord</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate, did he ever diſallow of this <hi>lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Adoration?</hi> no, but in his infancie it pleaſed him, to bee <hi>preſented in the Temple.</hi> And at twelve yeeres old to diſpute <hi>in the Temple,</hi> Luk. 2. And after his baptiſme, he daily <hi>taught in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> and <hi>preached in the Synagogues.</hi> After his aſcention where were his Apoſtles? but <hi>continually in the Temple,</hi> Luk. 24. Or where were the faithfull? but <hi>daily with one accord in the Temple,</hi> Act. 2.46.</p>
            <p>Now when the Temple was demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>Titus Veſpatian,</hi> not a ſtone left upon a ſtone, as our Saviour had foretold, Then <hi>Chriſtian Churches</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be frequent, which yet were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant afore in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> time; for ſee I pray you, what diſparitie hee puts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt ordinary houſes, and the houſe of God: <hi>What? have yee not houſes to eate and to drinke in, or deſpiſe yee the Church of God?</hi> 1. Cor. 11. Againe, <hi>Let your women keepe ſilence in the Churches,</hi> and let them aske their husbands at
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22580:11"/>home, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. Now let Saint <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſpeak for the next Generation — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, All to one place, all to the Temple of God, in his undoubted. Epiſtle to the <hi>Magneſians.</hi> As for ſucceding Ages, all teſtimonies are ſuperfluous; the furious edicts of perſecuting Tyrants for raſing and rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating Churches, abundantly ſhew how <hi>Churches</hi> did abound. And is not this enough, to put to ſilence thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable men with their ſectaries that ſurvive, who in the height of malice and ſacriledge, endeavoured preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly this laſt age, to lay deſolate and waſt, <hi>all the Synagogues of God in the land?</hi> What ſhould the Prophet have ſaid to ſuch a generation? <hi>O worſhip the Lord;</hi> Where? no matter where: in a Barne, or a Shop, or a Wood: no, but the Prophet hath told us where; and the practiſe of the Saints make it mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that before the Law, under the Law, and under the Goſpell, there have beene ever due to the celebration of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22580:12"/>Gods worſhip ſequeſtred places, either <hi>Altars,</hi> or <hi>Tabernacles,</hi> or <hi>Temples,</hi> or <hi>Churches,</hi> or <hi>Chappels,</hi> or the like; that wee are juſtly directed by the Prophet here, to a <hi>proper place,;</hi> Let us now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend to the <hi>properties</hi> of the place; And an <hi>holy</hi> place it is, a place of <hi>Holineſſe;</hi> and a <hi>beautifull</hi> place, <hi>the very beautie of Holineſſe,</hi> — <hi>O worſhip, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In atrio Sancto,</hi> or <hi>in Sanctuario,</hi> In his holy Courts, or in his holy Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for who can doubt but the <hi>beautie of Holineſſe</hi> muſt needs bee <hi>holy?</hi> And that apparantly in a double regard: Firſt, becauſe the place of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was hallowed ever, and ſet apart to holy uſes; for ſo were Altars afore the Law, and after them the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and after that the Temple; And by the ſame right Churches, and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels at this Day. The <hi>dedication</hi> of the Tabernacle, we have at large let down, <hi>Numb.</hi> 7. The <hi>dedication</hi> of the Temple, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8. And it ſtands with all good reaſon and religion, that houſes of God,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22580:12"/>be ſequeſtred now by ſolemne conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration, as well as heretofore. For wherefore I pray you, did <hi>Salomon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate the Temple? and after him <hi>Ezra</hi> the Prieſt upon the reſtauration? And the <hi>Prieſts</hi> againe under <hi>Iudas Macca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beus,</hi> when it had beene polluted? Or wherefore did <hi>Iacob</hi> conſecrate a pillar of ſtone <hi>by powring oyle upon it;</hi> Gen. 28. Did the Lord command him, or <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> or any of them all? where? it will no where be found. It was rectified rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and godly wiſedome, which dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them by a publique <hi>dedication,</hi> as it were by a publique <hi>declaration,</hi> to manifeſt to the world the religious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veiance of Sacred places, to Sacred uſes; And then it followes, that as <hi>Bethel</hi> of old, and the <hi>Sanctuary:</hi> ſo likewiſe our <hi>Bethels</hi> are holy, being ſolemnly <hi>hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>devoted</hi> in the name of God, and to the glory of God, as they were.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Holy</hi> againe, becauſe our Lord God, moſt holy, doth inhabite and poſſeſſe them, as his proper Manſion, or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22580:13"/>Houſe; for did he not take poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, when <hi>the Cloud covered the Tent, and the glory of the Lord filled the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle?</hi> Exod. 40.34. What did hee elſe by that ſacred inumbration, but take as it were Liverie and Seiſin? And juſt ſo it was at the finiſhing of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: <hi>The glory of the Lord filled the Houſe of the Lord,</hi> 1. Kings 8. And they were thereupon called and counted his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Place for ever after; by <hi>David, O thou that dwelleſt betweene the Cherubins,</hi> Pſal. 80. by our Saviour, <hi>Who ſo ſhall ſweare by the Temple, ſweareth by it, and by him that dwelleth therein,</hi> Matth. 23.21.</p>
            <p>And can any Chriſtian doubt, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hee bee preſent in our Chriſtian Congregations? where holy <hi>Prayers</hi> are powred forth, his holy <hi>Goſpel</hi> prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, his holy <hi>Sacraments</hi> adminiſtred, his moſt holy <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated. Is it not deepe infidelitie and hereſie, to thinke Chriſt to bee abſent from his Body and Blood? Moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:22580:13"/>preſent he is, though not by his <hi>glorious,</hi> yet in a ſingular way, by his <hi>gracious</hi> preſence. Yee may as well (ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) ſhut God out of Heaven,<note place="margin">S. Chryſ. horn. 36. in 1. Cor.</note> as exclude him hence. For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this indeed is Heaven upon Earth; and here <hi>the Tabernacle of God is with men, and God himſelfe is with them,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. 21. <hi>Holy</hi> then wee ſee, becauſe the Lord is there by his <hi>holy preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now it begins to be open day with us, we may clearely perceive, why the Prophet would have us worſhip rather in the place of <hi>holineſſe</hi> than elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where: Becauſe the Lord is ſure to be found there. And wee are to ſeeke the Lord, as well <hi>where,</hi> as <hi>while</hi> hee may be found. Where will yee enquire of the Maſter, but at his Houſe? And <hi>the Houſe of God is the Houſe of Prayer,</hi> Eſa. 56. Where ſhall yee hope to finde the King, ſo ſoone as in his Court? So the King of Heaven will be found <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in his holy Court, above any other place.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:22580:14"/>
            <p>True, the Lord will be found of his humble devout ſervants in what place ſoever; and I would have nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, to the prejudice of private prayer: <hi>For</hi> Moſes <hi>in the Sea,</hi> Iob <hi>on the Dunghill,</hi> Ieremie <hi>in the Dungeon,</hi> Daniel <hi>in the Den,</hi> Ionas <hi>in the Whale, the Children in the Furnace, S.</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Paul <hi>in Priſon, calling upon God, were heard,</hi> as S. <hi>Baſil</hi> noteth. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle would have men pray <hi>every where, lifting up holy hands,</hi> 1. Tim. 2. Yes, every where, with <hi>holy hands.</hi> But are <hi>holy hands</hi> every where? What ſhall the ſinner doe, that is deſtitute of <hi>holy hands?</hi> What elſe, but to the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the Publican? There he ſhall meete with holy hands, in the holy Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and may ſpeed the better, be graciouſly accepted for their ſakes, as <hi>Iobs</hi> friends for his ſake, <hi>Iob</hi> 42. In my devotions, let me joyne with the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, and then his prayer (I ſhall hope) will make way for mine: Nay, and how ſhall my charitie be augmented,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:22580:14"/>my zeale kindled, my faith confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, when I heare the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, <hi>quaſi manu factâ,</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore and <hi>ſend up an army of prayers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertull.</note> for the pardon of my ſinnes: For thus it is ever in theſe ſacred mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; All for every one, and every one for all, that God may be gracious and have mercy upon all; great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then we ſhould worſhip there.</p>
            <p>And ſo often as we worſhip there, would God wee would remember <hi>where</hi> we are, <hi>that the place whereon we ſtand is holy ground:</hi> It vvas certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part of the Prophets meaning, that the very name of <hi>Holineſſe</hi> ſhould make us beware of <hi>prophaneneſſe.</hi> He termes it rather a place of Holineſſe, than the Tabernacle, or the Temple; to put us in minde of that venerable, grave, religious behaviour, evermore requiſite and expected here. For <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe becommeth thy Houſe, O Lord, for ever,</hi> Pſal. 93. to put us in minde to <hi>looke well to our feete when wee goe to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22580:15"/>the Houſe of God,</hi> Eccl. 4. To <hi>our Feete,</hi> not to make that a walking place; and to our <hi>Tongues,</hi> not to make that a talking place; and to our <hi>Eyes,</hi> not to make that a gazing place. And he that <hi>whipt the buyers and ſellers out of the Temple,</hi> would he not, thinke we, have ſilenced our praters in the Houſe of Prayer, and have charged our Church-walkers to leave the Church? <hi>Antiquitie</hi> ſo underſtood it, I am ſure; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Hom. 36. in 1. Cor.</note> In the Church unlawfull even to ſpeake but to a neighbor (ſaith S. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) and much more unlawfull to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive &amp; drive a Bargaine there, as if at a Mart or common Market: And how unſufferable then, that the Church ſhould be made a place of rude con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and uncivill conteſtations?</p>
            <p>But was not <hi>Antiquitie</hi> too pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe? No: they knew <hi>Religion</hi> is upheld by nothing more than <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence;</hi> that wee can never bee too cleane in the Sanctuarie, nor
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22580:15"/>too holy in the place of Holineſſe, where we are to meete with our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and to worſhip the Lord moſt <hi>high,</hi> and moſt <hi>holy.</hi> Let us paſſe on now from this <hi>holy</hi> place (as it is holy) and behold it a while as <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull;</hi> for <hi>beautifull</hi> it is, as well as holy, even <hi>the beautie of Holineſſe; O worſhip &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Expoſitors finde themſelves at a loſſe, and therefore ſtrive to make it up as they may, by various expreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Some ſay, <hi>in Sanctuario magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fico,</hi> in the ſtately Sanctuarie: Some, <hi>in magnificentiâ Sanctitatis,</hi> in the ſumptuouſneſſe or magnificence of Sanctitie: Some, <hi>in ſplendore Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii,</hi> in the ſplendour or glory of his holy Place: Some, <hi>in decore Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis,</hi> in the comelineſſe or Beautie of Holineſſe. Now put them together, and the Place recommended, is holy, comely, ſtately, ſumptuous, glorious; not more holy, than comely; nor more ſacred, than ſumptuous: A
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22580:16"/>moſt fit Place this to worſhip the Lord in: <hi>O worſhip the Lord in the beautie of Holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is not our Prophet miſtaken heere? Or is not this combination made up of inconſiſtents? For, can Holy and Stately, Beautie and San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitie, runne in a Line? Yes, may and ought, as much as may be: and where they part and goe aſunder, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate of their perfection: for as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing magnifies Greatneſſe, more than Godlineſſe; ſo nothing ſets off Godlineſſe, more than Greatneſſe. Poore and godly, are as little eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the many, as poore and wiſe; and yee know what the Wiſe man ſayes and ſhewes too, <hi>The poore mans wiſdome is deſpis'd,</hi> Eccl. 9.16. And on the other ſide, what is a great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly man (without amendment) but like a great unſound Cedar, every day fitter and fitter for the fire? But where <hi>Greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>Goodneſſe, High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> and <hi>Holineſſe, Sanctitie</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limitie</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:22580:16"/>meet, there Gods worſhip is in the full, there God is magnified indeed; and wee cannot but hope, the Lord will goe on to magnifie with the full meaſure of his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings.</p>
            <p>And wee ſhall quickly perceive Gods worſhip to be advanced as well by the dignitie of the place, as the perſon: And it will not doe amiſſe, to appeale in this caſe to common experience; for doe vvee not finde our ſelves otherwiſe affected, vvhen vve come into a naked, deformed, ruinous Temple, adorned with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but duſt and cobwebs, and vvhen vve come into a goodly reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend beautifull Church, wherein we may behold on every ſide remarke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able teſtimonies of devout Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence? Doth not the very Fabricke and faſhion, and ſolemne accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation beget in our hearts a religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous regard, and venerable thoughts?</p>
            <p>True, a ſort of Chriſtians there are,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22580:17"/>ſo tranſelementated and refined, as to deſpiſe all ſuccours and ſupplies of this kinde, as matter of diſtraction, and palpable inducements to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition: Talke, as if God regarded no longer any other Temples, but the bodies and ſoules of his Saints. And we cheerefully profeſſe, wee can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver too carefully preſerve, the inward beautie of theſe living Temples; for that is the <hi>beautie of Holineſſe</hi> indeed; and if any man ſhall pollute this beautie, or <hi>defile this temple, him ſhall God deſtroy,</hi> 1. Cor. 3. But how the inward grace of theſe living Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, ſhould be thought prejudiciall to the outward grace of the beautie of Holineſſe, is I confeſſe beyond my capacitie.</p>
            <p>For whether wee looke backe to the manner of Gods Service under the <hi>Law,</hi> or to the choiſeſt times un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> wee ſhall ſoone diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover <hi>Beautie</hi> and <hi>Holineſſe</hi> ſweetly accorded, till the love of the World
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22580:17"/>had gotten the upper hand of the love of God. For firſt, what can wee almoſt imagine, more rich and gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous than the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> was? vvherein all the Inſtruments and Vtenſils were of pure Gold, even to the <hi>Snuff-diſhes,</hi> Exod. 25. And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, the <hi>Temple</hi> what was it elſe; but very matter of wonder and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment? a glorious Spectacle of admiration to all the World. When the Queene of <hi>Sheba</hi> beheld it, the majeſticall beautie and ſervice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſo filled her heart, <hi>that there was no more ſpirit in her,</hi> 1. Kings 10.5. And very memorable it is; when the foundation of the <hi>later Houſe</hi> was layd, the Fathers and ancient men mourned and wept, becauſe it was like to be leſſe glorious than the firſt, <hi>Ezr.</hi> 3.12. Now what might be the reaſon of this incredible magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in the firſt, or of this religious emulation in the ſecond Temple? Take the reaſon from King <hi>Salomon,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:22580:18"/>who had ſtudied the point; <hi>The houſe which I build is great, for great is our God above all Gods,</hi> 2. Chron. 2.5. And if — <hi>quia magnus Deus,</hi> be a good argument, the Lord at this day, is as <hi>great</hi> as ever, and then is this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as <hi>good</hi> as ever.</p>
            <p>And had not (thinke wee) the Founders of Churches in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome a ſpeciall Eye to his glorious Majeſtie, for whoſe ſervice they were erected? yes verily: This made <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the Great, and <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, and <hi>Charles</hi> the fourth, to honour the Goſpell of Chriſt with ſo many ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly monuments of their pietie all the world over: Saint <hi>Cyrill</hi> deſcribing one of them in Hieruſalem, calles it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Catech. 14.</note> A Church all adorned and emboſſed with ſilver and gold. And <hi>Euſebius</hi> reporting of the ſpacious and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Church at Tyre, which was built anew by the famous <hi>B. P. Paulinus,</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:22580:18"/>ſayes, the luſture and ſplendour was ſuch — <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Lib. 10.</note> as made beholders amazed to behold it. And generally thus it was, whereſoever Churches of note were repaired (which infidels had deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) they evermore added— <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 10.</note> a more exquiſite beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie than ever before; alleadging for themſelves, by way of encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>The glory of the latter houſe, ſhall be greater than that of the former;</hi> Hag. 2. and that of our Prophet, <hi>Great is the Lord, and greatly to bee praiſed in the Citie of our God,</hi> Pſal. 48.1.</p>
            <p>But yet it muſt bee granted, this Chriſtian zeale for the beautie of Holineſſe, was not every where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; decencie and comelineſſe in all the houſes of God, but — <hi>Magnificen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Sanctitatis,</hi> this ſtate of Holineſſe; Holineſſe in ſtate, was not uſually ſeene, ſave in Cities and populous Places, whither huge multitudes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorting, very ample, and capacious
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22580:19"/>Receits were requiſite, which anon by the bountifull largition of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouter Chriſtians, became as ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous as capacious: and there was no iniquitie in ſuch inaequalitie; For the beautie of <hi>Holineſſe</hi> doth well admit of <hi>Magis</hi> and <hi>Minus;</hi> worſhip, and <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> and beautie, like the three Graces, ſhould goe hand in hand; but yet ſo, as where more worſhippers, there more holineſſe, and then more beautie there, as a kinde of <hi>portion</hi> and dowrie of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</p>
            <p>The Iewes had their <hi>beautie of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe</hi> more conſpicuouſly in the <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle</hi> and the <hi>Temple;</hi> but Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians more eſpecially in their <hi>Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> and <hi>mother Churches;</hi> even ever ſince the Goſpell and Chriſtian Faith were well ſetled; And it is ſtrange to reade how the Iewes did excell in <hi>bountie,</hi> for better preſerving that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent <hi>beautie;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exerc. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>84.</note> For as <hi>Caſaubon</hi> and <hi>Cuneus</hi> have faithfully collected, all,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:22580:19"/>even they alſo of the diſperſion,<note place="margin">P. Cun. lib. 2. cap. 12. &amp; 23. Ex Ioſeph. lib. 16. cap. 10.</note> from all parts and quarters ſent yeerely Contributions to Hieruſalem for the maintenance of the Temple; Becauſe <hi>they delighted in the ſtones thereof, and had pitie on the duſt thereof,</hi> Pſal. 102.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot but congratulate the preſent times, wherein the <hi>Beautie of Holineſſe</hi> in Citie and Countrey ſeemes to revive and flouriſh as never more: It argues Religion hath life in it, and that wee are in love with Religion: And I beſeech you give mee leave to condeſcend a little to particulars, and to magnifie the Lord in the words of <hi>Ezra</hi> the Prieſt. <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be the Lord God of our fathers who hath put ſuch a thing as this in the Kings heart, to beautifie the houſe of the Lord which is in Hieruſalem,</hi> Ezra 7.27. And bleſſed bee thoſe many Worthies which have ſtrengthned the hands of the workemen, to take away the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach from <hi>Iſrael</hi> by removing the <hi>abomination of deſolation.</hi> And bleſſed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:22580:20"/>be all that incourage the worke by their <hi>cheerefull beneficence,</hi> even to the poore widow, that ſhall <hi>caſt in her two mites;</hi> Let them proſper upon earth, and let their names be recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Booke of Life. And oh how were it to be wiſhed, that they which were at laying the <hi>firſt ſtone,</hi> might live to behold the <hi>conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> That they, and all the Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, and above all our moſt <hi>gracious Zerubbabel,</hi> might (when all is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed) worſhip the Lord, in that <hi>beautie of Holineſſe;</hi> Howſoever <hi>this ſhall bee written for the generations to come, and the people which ſhall be crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhall praiſe the Lord</hi> for this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable onſet. For what can make a more honourable teſtimony, or tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er evidence, of our unfeined eſteeme of Holineſſe, of our love to God, of our zeale for his Goſpell, than thus to reach out a liberall hand to the <hi>ſupportation,</hi> and a bountifull hand to the <hi>exornation</hi> of that ſacred edifice,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22580:20"/>where from age to age beyond all diſcovery, Holineſſe hath had her habitation? As for <hi>Tatnai,</hi> and <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therboſnai,</hi> and <hi>Sanballat,</hi> open or clandeſtine enemies to the beauty of Holineſſe, <hi>Fill their faces with ſhame, that they may ſeeke thy name, O Lord;</hi> That we, and they, and all that lay claime to true Holineſſe, may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre the <hi>beauty of Holineſſe</hi> before all other <hi>beauties,</hi> and with cleane hands, and pure hearts, delight to worſhip the Lord, in the proper place of his Worſhip, <hi>the beauty of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> I haue done at laſt with the properties of the place, <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>beautifull;</hi> Now followes the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets <hi>entreaty</hi> which I ſhall treate of in very few words, and ſo conclude; <hi>O worſhip the Lord in the beauty of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take it joyntly together, and it is not more a <hi>Precept</hi> than a <hi>Prayer;</hi> a very emphaticall obſecration, full of holy importunitie, and which argues
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:22580:21"/>in our Princely Prophet an extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie love to the Place and the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice here commended; that his chiefe delight was there: For, <hi>How amiable are thy Tabernacles, O Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Pſ. 84. And how diſconſolate, when hee was driven thence? <hi>Woe is mee. that I am conſtrained to dwell in Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſech, and to have my habitation among the Tents of Kedar,</hi> Pſ. 120. ſeemes to envie the filly Birds; <hi>The Sparrowes and Swallowes may lay their young even by thine Altars, O Lord of Hoſts, my King and my God:</hi> nor ſo deſirous though to be there alone, but there with his people; <hi>I was glad when they ſaid unto me, We will goe into the Houſe of the Lord,</hi> Pſ. 122. It joyed him to be ſeene, <hi>In medio Eccleſiae,</hi> in the midſt of the Congregation will I prayſe thee, Pſ. 22. Hee would pay his Vowes (in an exemplarie way) <hi>in the preſence of all his people,</hi> Pſ. 116. And wee cannot otherwiſe under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him here; Come children,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:22580:21"/>hearken unto me, doe as yee ſee mee doe; <hi>adorate</hi> and <hi>adorabo</hi> went to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, we may be ſure: And a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſight it was, to ſee Religion coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced, and the people religious, not more by his Regall <hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Edicts,</hi> than his <hi>Preſence</hi> and <hi>Practice;</hi> Now <hi>bleſſed are the people that be in ſuch a caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Looke we then to the practice of King <hi>David,</hi> what he was wont to doe in Gods Houſe, and wee ſhall ſoone diſcerne why hee is ſo earneſt to ſend us thither. Thither went <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> as well for <hi>reſolution</hi> as <hi>devotion:</hi> and his religious attention, was a good part of his adoration there; <hi>I will hearken what the Lord God will ſay, Pſal.</hi> 85. <hi>Et quaeram in Templo ejus,</hi> and I will enquire in his Temple, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27. And he tells us, hee could not be ſatisfied, <hi>till hee went into the Sanctuary of God, Pſal.</hi> 73. For the Sanctuary of old was the ſet place for ſatisfaction in doubtfull caſes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22580:22"/>from <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>David;</hi> — <hi>omnis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus qui habebat aliquam quaeſtionem,</hi> Exod. 33. All that had ought to ſay, any doubt to bee reſolved, reſorted thither for expedition: Prince and People, all without exception.</p>
            <p>And now it is a cleere caſe, it might vvell import him as a <hi>King</hi> to be ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in this point, that his people vvould goe and receive inſtruction in publique, in the place appointed, the right place; becauſe Conventicles, and private meetings, under colour of Religion, too often ſerve unto dangerous practiſes; Seditious o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, and turbulent poſitions have beene ever firſt <hi>invented</hi> and <hi>vented</hi> in private. There it is, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory pens, and ſawcie tongues are thought <hi>conſciencious,</hi> becauſe <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious,</hi> and hee commonly reputed the <hi>beſt man,</hi> that is the <hi>worſt ſubject.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or conſider him (if yee pleaſe) as a <hi>Prophet:</hi> ſo I am ſure he could not be too earneſt for worſhip in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22580:22"/>For the only way this, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Religion and the truth untain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to have <hi>Holineſſe</hi> duely taught, in the <hi>beautie of Holineſſe.</hi> Your inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingling and adulterate doctrines have beene ſtill begotten in private, and have paſſed by peece-meale from the <hi>Chamber</hi> to the <hi>Chappell,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Church;</hi> For when or where I pray you, did the envious man ſowe his tares? it was, <hi>dormientibus hominibus</hi> while men ſlept; in all likelihood in ſome private meeting about mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, when the watchmen of Iſrael were aſleepe. Wee may not doubt, but <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>truth</hi> both depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, that we aſſemble to worſhip the Lord, in the proper place of his worſhip.</p>
            <p>But <hi>David</hi> (they will ſay) though a <hi>King</hi> and a <hi>Prophet,</hi> was under the <hi>Law,</hi> and is he a fit preſident for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours of the <hi>Goſpell?</hi> Let them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peale then (if they will) from <hi>David,</hi> to the ſonne of <hi>David</hi> our bleſſed <hi>Saviour.</hi> And how ſtood he affected?
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:22580:23"/>That he was all in all for the <hi>publique,</hi> moſt manifeſt it is by the good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion which he made, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 18.20. <hi>I ſpake openly to the world, I ever taught in the Synagogue and in the Temple whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Iewes daily reſort, and in ſecret have I ſaid nothing.</hi> Heare this, you that love to whiſper it in a corner; that ſtand ſo much for <hi>Privatus ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis,</hi> a private ſpirit, or a private bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in a private place: how direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary are you to Chriſt? you for-<hi>omnia</hi> Chriſt for-<hi>nihil in occulto,</hi> good Chriſtians in the meane while.</p>
            <p>For that our Saviour could not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with this <hi>Parlour-preaching,</hi> and theſe <hi>Chamber-congregations,</hi> plaine it ſeemes by that charge which he left to his Church, <hi>Matt.</hi> 24.26. <hi>If they ſhall ſay unto you, behold hee is in the deſart, goe not forth: behold he is in the ſecret chambers, beleeve them not.</hi> For I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you where hath beene the mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting place of our <hi>Anti-Canonicall Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts,</hi> and where have they enacted their <hi>Antiſynodicall Sanctions,</hi> but, <hi>in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22580:23"/>deſerto,</hi> or <hi>in Cubiculo?</hi> there is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no beleeving them. Alas, when they have ſet up once in private, the great <hi>idoll</hi> of their own <hi>imaginations,</hi> &amp; have conſulted their grand <hi>Oracle,</hi> I was ſaying, at the <hi>Idols table,</hi> they will not ſticke to ſay and decree any thing. No appealing then from <hi>David</hi> to the ſon of <hi>David</hi> in this caſe, both are for the publique, for the ſolemne aſſembly both, for the Temple and the <hi>holy</hi> place, the <hi>beautie of Holineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, repreſent we <hi>David</hi> to our thoughts as a <hi>King</hi> or a <hi>Prophet,</hi> we muſt needs confeſſe that this en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treatie here is to ſingular good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that it makes very much for <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>unitie,</hi> and <hi>pietie.</hi> Now the God of peace and truth leade us into all truth, and bring us unto that peace which paſſeth all underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; bring us all in mercy from the <hi>beautie of Holineſſe</hi> in the kingdome of <hi>Grace,</hi> to the <hi>Holy of Holies</hi> in the kingdome of <hi>Glory.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:22580:24"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22580:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
